Lauren Oey

loey812@gmail.com (862) 223-9228 Github LinkedIn

SUMMARY

Computational research scientist with 9+ years of experience developing generative statistical models, testing models with self-programmed human behavioral experiments, and building analysis pipelines to interpret and query rich, structured datasets. I am always eager to strategically select from or add new tools to my machine learning and text analysis toolkit, spanning language models, mixed-effects regression, clustering, word embeddings, network analysis, information measures, etc. My overarching goal is to improve how AI caters to human beliefs and values.

EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University

2023-Present

- Integrated Phaser physics engine & canvas drawing to innovate a unique, engaging behavioral experiment (JavaScript, CSS, HTML, PHP)
- Evaluate data to identify improvement in data collection and executed improvements (SQL, R)
- Comparing image variability using mutual information measures (python, pandas, PIL, seaborn)
- Applying LLMs to strings of stroke coordinates to develop artificial generative agents that "draw" alongside people

Computational Researcher, Computational Cognition Lab + Cognitive Tools Lab

2018-2023

- Developed statistical and economic generative models of human communication and pragmatics (lying & lie detection) in R
- Created web app (rshiny) to interpret & visualize model behavior across parameter changes
- Applied machine learning techniques (e.g. LDA topic models with stm, word embeddings for semantic analysis, k-means clustering) to webscraped 34,000+ text documents w/ network structure (python, beautifulsoup4, pdfminer)
- Trained & fine-tuned LSTM & n-gram LMs on the Reddit corpus to measure word entropy (PyTorch)
- Published 3 journal articles, 5 conference papers, awarded ~\$200,000 in grants, managed 8 undergrad researchers

Research Intern, Center for the Study of Language & Information, Stanford University

Summer 201

- Programmed multi-agent web experiments in interdisciplinary team (computer science & psychology researchers)
- Analyzed text free response data using CoreNLP tools to evaluate semantic and pragmatic content

Research Assistant, Human Language Processing Lab + Computation & Language Lab

2015-2018

- Led honors thesis (programmed multiple experiments, applied predictive models & mixed-effects regression models), resulting in conference talks & best talk award
- Collaborated with 3-person team of students to replicate & expand on accented speech processing study
- Assisted in teaching 6 data science, statistics, computer science, & linguistics courses

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python (pandas, seaborn), R (tidyverse, rshiny), SQL, JavaScript, Java

Other: PyTorch, HTML, CSS, LaTeX, Markdown, Git, Unix Shell, Mechanical Turk, CloudResearch, MariaDB

EDUCATION

University of California, San Diego

2023

Ph.D. in **Experimental Psychology** (GPA: 4.0)

University of Rochester

2018

B.S. in Brain and Cognitive Sciences, Honors in Research, Magna cum laude (GPA: 3.85)

B.A. in Statistics & Linguistics (triple major); Minor in Computer Science

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Oey, L. A. & Vul, E. (2023). Accurate approximations about the truth from literally false messages. *Computational Brain & Behavior*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42113-023-00187-0

- Oey, L. A., Schachner, A., & Vul, E. (2023). Designing and detecting lies by reasoning about other agents. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: General*, 152(2), 346-362. https://doi.org/10.1037/xge0001277
- Huey, H.*, Oey, L. A.*, Lloyd, H. S. & Fan, J. E. (2023). How do communicative goals guide which data visualizations people think are effective? In M. Goldwater, F. K. Anggoro, B. K. Hayes, & D. C. Ong (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 2229-2236).
- Oey, L. A. & Vul, E. (2022). Inferring truth from lies. In J. Culbertson, A. Perfors, H. Rabagliati, & V. Ramenzoni (Eds.), Proceedings of the 44th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (pp. 1469-1475).
- DeStefano, I.*, Oey, L. A.*, Brockbank, E., & Vul, E. (2021). Integration by parts: Collaboration and topic structure in the CogSci community. *Topics in Cognitive Science*, 13(2), 399-413. https://doi.org/10.1111/tops.12526
- Oey, L. A. & Vul, E. (2021). Lies are crafted to the audience. In T. Fitch, C. Lamm, H. Leder, & K. Teßmar-Raible (Eds.), Proceedings of the 43rd Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (pp. 791-797).
- Oey, L.*, DeStefano, I.*, Brockbank, E., & Vul, E. (2020). Formalizing interdisciplinary collaboration in the CogSci community. In S. Denison, M. L. Mack, Y. Xu, & B. C. Armstrong (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 474-480).
- Oey, L. A., Schachner, A., & Vul, E. (2019). Designing good deception: Recursive theory of mind in lying and lie detection. In A. K. Goel, C. M. Seifert, & C. Freksa (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 41st Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 897-903). Montreal, QB: Cognitive Science Society.
- Oey, L. A., Mollica, F., & Piantadosi, S. T. (2018). Adults use gradient similarity information in compositional rules. In T. T. Rogers, M. Rau, X. Zhu, & C. W. Kalish (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 40th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 842-847). Austin, TX: Cognitive Science Society.

FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS

ACM SIGHPC Computational & Data Science Fellowship (\$45,000)	2021-2023
Diverse Intelligences Summer Institute Fellowship, Templeton World Charity Fund	2021
Computational Modeling Prize in Applied Cognition, Cognitive Science Society (\$1,000)	2020
William James Prize Honorable Mention (2 nd best paper), Society for Philosophy and Psychology	2019
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (\$138,000)	2018-2023
Norman Henry Anderson Graduate Fellowship, UCSD (\$5,000)	2018-2019
Competitive EDGE Fellowship, UCSD (\$4,000)	2018
Real World Communication Student Travel Award	2018
President's Award (best talk), University of Rochester, Undergrad Research Exposition (Social Sciences)	2018